Guide to the KVOS Channel 12 Film Records 1961-1967
Western Washington University, Heritage Resources
- Webster Reports, 1961-1966; Series I
  - W-33 Rebel in Kilts (Farley Mort), 1965 December 26 (Box-reel 11/2)
    Description: Canadian author and self-described anarchist Farley Mowat is the guest for the entire episode. Half of the show is devoted to discussing his most recent book West Viking, and the medieval Scandinavian settlements in Greenland and Newfoundland. Mowat mentions such Viking explorers as Eric the Red and Leif Ericson. Other subjects discussed include anarchy and anarchism, Eskimo rights, aboriginal rights, freedom, and Mowat’s disgust with modern society. Webster raises accusations of anti-Americanism and anti-Canadianism. Amongst Mowat’s more famous works are Never Cry Wolf, A Whale for the Killing, and Sea of Slaughter.
  - W-34 Snob Mob, 1966 March 27 (Box-reel 12/1)
    Description: The brand-new Canadian national magazine believed to be called Parallel (or something that sounds like Parallel) is featured in this episode, which is divided between two interviews. The first is with publisher Douglas Cohen, who defends the launching of this new multi-topical publication aimed at “the intelligent elite” (hence “snob mob”). Subjects for the magazine are to include art, literature, politics, social issues, etc – tailored for the Canadian reader. Despite a promising early circulation of 90,000, Cohen explains why the magazine is expected to lose 25,000.00 in the first year. The second interview is with Editor-in-chief Peter Deveraux, who discusses the magazine and general political and social issues.
  - W-35 Name of Justice, 1966 May 1 (Box-reel 12/2)
    Description: Isabel LeBourdais and her new book
    The Trial of Steven Truscott
    is the subject of this episode. Fourteen year old Steven Truscott, in 1959, had been convicted of the rape and murder of his twelve year old schoolmate Lynne Harper. But LeBourdais was convinced that the trial had been a miscarriage of justice, and that Truscott, then the youngest person ever on Canada’s death row, was innocent. She spent four years researching and gathering evidence before releasing the book. However, despite the compelling evidence in LeBourdais’ book, Truscott never received a new trial. Although paroled in 1969, Truscott still struggles to clear his name today (2005). An unnamed individual replaces Jack Webster as interviewer on this episode.
- Channel 12 Specials, 1962-1967; Series II
  - If the Bomb Survives, Can We?, 1962 June 1 (Box-reel 13/1)
    Length: 8:15 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): fair (scraps of footage; fragmentary). Image is improperly exposed.
    Duplicate: VHS, DVD, digital
    Description: Footage of a small peace rally at WWC (Western Washington College of Education; soon to become Western Washington State College, and eventually Western Washington University). First 2:20 minutes are soundless footage of protesters, students, counter-protesters, placards and signs. Slogans on signs include “Bomb = Death, Peace = Life” and “Perpetual War: Man, It’s Profitable!” From 2:20 to 5:10 English Professor Arthur Hicks delivers an anti-war speech with numerous references to Moscow and Washington D.C. (Cold War), after which silent footage of a dozen or so protesters marching down route 99. In the final minute Al Swift interviews three of the marchers. See S-8 for a different perspective on nuclear war. See also S-40 for more protest footage.
  - S-3 European Common Market and You, 1962 July 6 (Box-reel 13/2)
    Length: 30:37 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): Good
    Duplicate: DVD Only
    Sound: Yes
    Description: Several politicians from both Washington State and British Columbia are interviewed. They discuss the impact the European Common Market will have on Washington and British Columbia as well as its impact on the United States and Canada as a whole.
  - S-4 Girls, Glitter and Gracie (Soft porn at Seattle Worlds Fair), 1962 August 10 (Box-reel 13/3)
    Length: 24:45 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): good overall (footage of the fashion show is improperly exposed).
    Description: Chorus line and cabaret producer and promoter Gracie Hansen is interviewed for twenty minutes. Her show “Gracie Hansen’s Paradise” was a prime adult entertainment attraction at the 1962 Seattle World’s Fair. She discusses her early career, the background of the show, the showgirls and other performers, etc. Soundless footage prior to the interview shows a sign reading “peep,” a large sign reading “Night in Paradise” and footage of dancers donning costumes and applying makeup. Soundless footage of a fashion show follows the interview, with women modeling polka-dot dresses, swimwear, and lingerie.
  - S-7 Operation: Cooperation (Air Raid Shelters), 1962 October 3 (Box-reel 14/1)
    Sound: yes (except first 2:30 minutes)
    Description: This episode is devoted to a ceremony held at the Peace Arch on September 22, 1962, celebrating the civil defense cooperation agreement recently signed between Washington State and British Columbia. Specifically aimed at enhancing cross-border coordination in the event of a nuclear attack, a key provision of the treaty calls for a Vancouver evacuation route to run through Whatcom County: up H Street in Blaine, and on to Sumas. Footage shows Canadian and American politicians hammering nails to erect a dispersal route sign at the border. Footage includes short speeches made by several officials praising international cooperation, both the interior and exterior of the Washington State Civil Defense Mobile Command Post bus, Canadian and American troops marching back and forth under the Peace Arch while a marching band plays, and food being prepared for and eaten by the troops. Amongst several people interviewed are British Columbia Provincial Secretary W.D. Bligh and Washington State Lieutenant Governor John Sherbert.
  - S-8 Religion and Science in the Nuclear Age, 1962 October 17 (Box-reel 14/2)
    Description: Episcopal priest and Nuclear Physicist Dr. William G. Pollard is interviewed throughout this episode. Pollard, a former Manhattan Project research scientist, discusses the potential conflict between science and religion, and asserts that they complement rather than contradict each other. Issues surrounding nuclear proliferation, the atom bomb, the church stance on the nuclear arms race, disarmament, arms control, and the effectiveness of fallout shelters predominate. But Pollard also speculates philosophically about the nature of war and warfare, dimensions of reality and existence, and relativity as perceived by physical science and Christianity. See 13/1 and S-40 for a different perspective on nuclear war.
  - S-10 God, Allah, and Ju Ju, 1962 October 15 (Box-reel 15/1)
    Description: Dr. James McAree, Associate Professor of History at Western Washington State College, discusses religion in emerging Africa with Unitarian Reverend Jack Mendelson, who has recently published the book “God, Allah, and Ju Ju.” Christianity (especially Catholicism), Islam, and indigenous religions (lumped as “Ju Ju”) are compared and contrasted, with regard to their impact on African culture and consciousness. Mendelson asserts that Christianity is a declining force in Africa, while Islam is on the rise – partially due to more effective missionary techniques. So-called “Ju Ju”, according to Mendelson, is crucial to African identity.
  - S-11 The Race for Washington (Senator Warren G. Magnuson and Richard Christianson), 1962 November 1 (Box-reel 15/2)
    Film Quality (Original): good (but no lead on film; footage begins abruptly).
    Description: Four politicians are interviewed prior to the 1962 senatorial and congressional election: incumbent senator Warren G Magnuson (Democrat) and his opponent Richard Christiansen (Republican) as well as incumbent representative Alfred Westland (Republican) and his opponent Milo E. Moore (Democrat). Magnuson is interviewed for the first ten minutes, and briefly touches upon a range of issues including Medicare, trade, the Kennedy Administration, communism, and his unwillingness to engage his opponent in a televised debate. Christiansen, a former Lutheran Minister, is interviewed for the next ten minutes and focuses primarily on his campaign strategy, although he also takes time to condemn communism. Both interviews touch upon the different political climate in Washington East and West of the Cascades. Westland, of Washington’s Second Congressional District, is interviewed for four minutes, and offers a position on Whatcom County lumber issues. Moore, a former Washington State Fisheries Director, mentions his plan to turn Drayton Harbor and Terrell Creek (Birch Bay) into fish farms.
  - S-12 Key to the College Door, 1963 February 13 (Box-reel 16/1)
    Description: Interviews with Western Washington State College (which would later become Western Washington University) administrators about college-related issues. Interviewees include WWSC President James L. Jarrett and Dean of Men C.W. MacDonald (known as Bill MacDonald). Topics include preparing for college, reasons for going to college, alternatives to college, admissions criteria, the cost of a college education, loans, and scholarships. Interviews with a selected panel of students explore their attitudes towards college, and related issues such as study habits, financial management, and extracurricular activities. Silent footage of the college is interspersed, with shots of Old Main, Bond Hall, the Carver Gym, etc. See S-20A for related material.
  - S-13 Room for the 3 R's (Sehome High School bond issue), 1963 March 6 (Box-reel 16/2)
    Length: 39 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): Much of this reel, especially the 1st half, in poor condition with many breaks and inadequate splicing.
    Description: The first ten minutes of footage lack dialogue or narration, and show the crowded hallways of Bellingham High School, as well as external views of the buildings. The balance of the reel intersperses similar footage (including aerial shots of the Bellingham High) with interviews about the necessity of building a second high school in Bellingham. Topics include a new municipal bond issue, site selection, and (at length) philosophical differences between those favoring four versus three year high schools. Differing perspectives on secondary education are reviewed. Interviewees are not identified. See also BM-3 for more on this topic
  - S-14 Castro Revisited, 1963 April 24 (Box-reel 17/1)
    Length: 28:30 minutes
    Description: Sergio Rojas, a defector from the Fidel Castro regime in Cuba, is interviewed for the first twenty-two minutes. He discusses his reasons for supporting the Cuban revolution against the Baptista government, and why he eventually turned against Castro. He paints a grim picture of living conditions in Cuba, and condemns communism – claiming to have been unaware that that Casto’s rebellion had anything to do with communism. He calls upon the United States to support an insurrection against Castro – two years after the failed Bay of Pigs invasion. The Cuban Missile Crisis and Khrushchev are mentioned frequently. Professor John Wuest of Western Washington State College (later Western Washington University) is interviewed for the balance of the reel, and analyzes the preceding interview. He criticizes Rojas’ call for U.S. support without allowing greater U.S. involvement in a subsequent political restructuring of Cuba.
  - BM-3 Shall Bellingham Build a New High School?, Undated (Box-reel 17/2)
    Length: 18 minutes
    Description: Al Swift interviews Dave Mintz, chairman of the Bellingham Citizen’s Education Committee, about the approaching March 12 (1963?) vote on whether to fund the construction of a second Bellingham High School. Issues discussed include population growth, increasing family size, site selection, the municipal bond, taxes, and educational philosophy. Dave Mintz was also vice-president and general manager of KVOS television. See also S-13 for more on this topic.
  - BM-4 Tatayama, Undated (Box-reel 17/3)
    Length: 8 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): Poor. Fragmentary footage, scraps
    Duplicate: VHS only
    Sound: no
    Description: Soundless footage of Bellingham’s sister city of Tatayama, Japan. Buildings, cityscape, people eating and drinking sake.
  - S-16 Camelot, 1963 August (Box-reel 18/1)
    Description: Three cast members of the hit Broadway musical “Camelot” are interviewed on the eve of the play’s opening at the Queen Elizabeth Theatre in Vancouver. Actor Robert Peterson has assumed the role of Sir Lancelot from original cast member Robert Goulet. Arthur Treacher, who appears with his sheepdog, has taken over the role of King Arthur from Richard Burton. Actress Catherine Grayson has replaced Julie Andrews as Guinevere, and is accompanied by three cocker spaniels. All three interviews are extremely personal, with Arthur Treacher’s being exceptionally amusing due to his forceful, eccentric personality. Treacher is known for his roles in over seventy films, as well as the chain of fish and chips restaurants which bears his name.
  - Editorial 1, Undated (Box-reel 18/2)
    Length: 5:30 each (11:00 total).
    Description: These two short editorials by Al Swift of KVOS concern the use of Whatcom County funds derived from the sale of timber on federal forest lands within the county. County commissioners E.R. Haxton, Henry Halvorson, and Archie Truax had decided to apply the entire annual amount towards the road fund (citing damage from a bad winter), instead of splitting it with the county schools as precedent dictated. The commissioners also cited an annual deficit for the Lummi Ferry. Swift decries the officials’ refusal to be interviewed about their decision, and accuses them of denying the public’s right to know. Transparency of government is at the root of the principle that Swift is defending. These editorials aired on consecutive nights.
  - Editorial 2, Undated (Box-reel 18/3)
  - S-20A A Professor Looks at his College (Part 1 of 2), 1964 October 24 (Box-reel 19/1)
    Length: 29:30 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): good (some minor splicing required).
    Description: This reel consists of narration superimposed over images of student life at Western Washington State College (later Western Washington University), chosen from over four and a half hours of footage and interviews. Eight professors contribute to the commentary: Katherine Carroll, Charles Flora, Arthur Hicks, James McAree, Richard Reynolds, Herbert Taylor, Ralph Thompson, and Mary Watrous. They opine about their educational philosophies, teaching styles, students and the college experience, extracurricular activities, etc. Different views on the best way to provide a college education are offered. Footage includes the campus - Old Main, Wilson Library, the future site of Red Square, the Carver Gym; footage of professors lecturing, students in laboratories, students performing music and creating visual arts, playing football, etc. Off-campus footage includes biology or zoology students exploring tide-pools along Bellingham’s shoreline, and visiting Whatcom Falls. See S-20B for extra footage related to this episode, and S-12 for more on WWSC in the 1960's.
  - S-20B A Professor Looks at his College(Part 2 of 2), 1964 October 24 (Box-reel 19/2)
    Description: This reel consists of extra, soundless footage taken for the creation of S-20A. Subject matter is heavily intermingled. Lots of shots of tide-pool hunting (see above), and Whatcom Falls. More footage of football, cheerleading, and a large bonfire – possibly homecoming. Extensive footage from still photos of the smashing of a piano while a crowd of students looks on. See S-20A for the actual episode, and S-12 for more on WWSC in the 1960's.
  - S-21 The First R, 1963 November 14 (Box-reel 20/1)
    Description: Dr. Donald Durrell, Professor of Education at Boston University and nationally recognized authority on the teaching of reading, is interviewed by Dr. James L. Jarrett, President of Western Washington State College (later Western Washington University). Durrell discusses the best approaches to teaching reading to young children. Topics that are raised include phonics, flashcards, cursive writing, spelling, parental preparation, pronunciation, child psychology, education, educational philosophy, and the importance of elementary school libraries. Emphasis on kindergarten, first grade.
  - S-22 Inside Lake Whatcom: Part I (with Dr.Charles Flora), 1963 November 21 (Box-reel 21/1)
    Length: 31 minutes
    Sound: yes (except for outdoor scenes)
    Description: Bellingham Mayor and Chairman of the Water Board John E Westford introduces the subject of Lake Whatcom, and the city funded 1963 study of its water quality. Professor Charles Flora, who co-conducted the study, then gives an informative lecture about the lake, using a large scale model (1 to 2400 feet) of the lake in the science building at Western Washington State College (later Western Washington University). He describes the physiogeography of the lake, which serves as a reservoir for the City of Bellingham. Flora places the volume of the lake, which is fed by the Nooksack River, at 778,000 acre feet of water. Issues such as drinking water pollution are raised, but in less detail than in part 2 (S-23). The balance of the reel consists of footage of experiments being conducted on the lake. See S-23 for part 2
  - S-23 Inside Lake Whatcom: Part II (with Dr.Charles Flora), 1963 November 21 (Box-reel 21/2)
    Sound: yes (except outdoor scenes)
    Description: The first seven minutes of the reel contains footage of experiments being conducted out on Lake Whatcom. From 7 to 13 minutes, Dr. Kraft discusses the importance of temperature readings, and explains a chart illustrating a thermocline. At 14:50 minutes he returns to describe measurements taken of oxygen and bacteria levels. He describes the varying amounts of choliform bacteria in the lake, which is indicative of fecal pollution. He closes with a warning about the adverse impact of development, contaminants, and pollutants on the drinking water supply. See S-22 for part 1
  - S-24 The Mark of Connelly, 1963 December 25 (Box-reel 22/1)
    Duplicate: VHS, DVD,digital
    Description: Writer, director, playwright, Yale University Drama Professor, and theatre critic Marc Connelly is interviewed for the entire reel. The first ten minutes focuses on his influential 1930 all-black production Green Pastures, which adapts old testament stories to Southern Black folklore. Issues raised include race relations, racism, minorities, segregation, the theatre, and literature. The second half of the interview emphasizes Connelly’s early days as a New York journalist, and his early collaborations with George Kauffman.
  - S-25 The Varied World of Ben Avital, 1964 January 1 (Box-reel 23/1)
    Description: Al Swift interviews Jewish activist Benad Avital, who was then the Israeli consul to the 13 western states. The London-born Avital discusses a broad range of topics, based upon his varied life experiences. As a filmmaker and film producer in the 1930’s and early 40’s, he worked on the British production of Henry V, starring Laurence Olivier. He also made films in Israel in the mid 1950’s. After serving in the RAF signal corps during the second world war, Avital became an active member in AJEX – the Association of Jewish Ex-Servicemen, an anti-fascist protest organization. He describes the tactics used to undermine Sir Oswald Mosley’s British Fascism movement. Next, he discusses life on an Israeli Kibbutz, including the practice of communal child-rearing. He also worked on a cooperative farm. He goes into some detail about his subsequent role as Israeli press officer during the Sinai conflict (the Six Days War), and examines both the causes and results of the war. The ongoing Arab – Israeli tensions, and Middle East turmoil, are at issue. He also comments upon the trial of Adolf Eichmann, and addresses criticism of the kidnapping of the infamous Nazi – often considered to be the architect of the holocaust.
  - S-26 The Port of Bellingham, 1964 February 6 (Box-reel 23/2)
    Film Quality (Original): film requires at least 3 splices.
    Description: Al Swift takes a look at the Port of Bellingham, with an emphasis on its contributions to growth and development. Several port administrators (unidentified) comment on the range of port activities at its various properties, including the Port Shipping Terminal Facility, Squalicum Harbor, South Bellingham properties, Blaine Boat Harbor, the airport (then served by one commercial airline: West Coast Airlines), and the Mountainview Industrial Site. Jim Brooks, Vice-president of the Whatcom County Industrial Development Council, discusses ways to attract businesses and private enterprise to the area, as well as issues related to shipping. Interviews and commentary are interspersed with aerial and panoramic footage of the Bellingham waterfront, the airport (including cockpit footage of the runway from a landing plane), and other areas in the county. Footage of waterfront industry includes processing fish into Sea Freez brand fishsticks, as well as Wakefield’s King Crab. See S-37 for more on industrial development in Whatcom County
  - Alaska Earthquake- The Day After, 1964 April 2 (Box-reel 24/1)
    Film Quality (Original): fair- good
    Sound: no (other than brief newscast at beginning).
    Description: After a brief introductory newscast by reporter Andy Anderson, this reel focuses on the massive destruction wrought on Kodiak City, on Kodiak Island, Alaska, by the 1964 earthquake. The March 27, 1964 quake was then (and is still) the largest earthquake to ever strike the United States. The devastation of Kodiak was caused by a series of accompanying tidal waves. The tsunami aftermath is well-illustrated by this dramatic footage of the town, showing ships smashed to bits amongst the ruins of buildings. Community relief efforts are also captured. See also S-27B
  - Alaska Earthquake- The Day After (also on videocassette), 1964 April 2 (Box-reel 24/2)
    Length: 28:40 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): fair - good
    Sound: no (other than introduction)
    Description: The majority of this reel repeats footage from the preceding reel (S-27A). Additional footage includes an extra introduction with background about Kodiak City, a minute and a half of extra commentary (at 22:30 minutes), and about five minutes of additional damage images. See S-27A
  - S-28 A Forest of Learning (Bellingham primary grade forestry unit), 1964 April 16 (Box-reel 25/1)
    Length: 6 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): short scraps of footage
    Description: This short reel features two minutes of soundless footage of children in the woods, followed by an unidentified man (from the Bellingham School District?) talking briefly about the school district’s arboretum acquired for educational purposes. Forestry, and forest conservation education are mentioned. Footage lacks explanatory context.
  - S-32 Our Public Schools (Elizabeth Kuntz), 1964 August 20 (Box-reel 25/2)
    Length: 25:30 minutes